ttpm.com 2006-05-04

# Twin Tier Pysician Management

|   
---  
|   
---  
  
**Home Care** \- Locally monitored and managed home care services and equipment. 

**Health System** \- An economic alternative to rising insurance costs. 

**Managed Care** \- Medicaid Managed Care Program simplifies reimbursements. 

**Referral Service** \- Assists patients in obtaining a timely appointment with a physician. 

**Holter Service** \- We offer 24 hour holter monitoring and scanning.

| 

Privacy Policy - Twin Tier Physician Management, Inc.

**NOTICE OF PRIVACY PRACTICES**

This notice describes how medical information about you may be used and disclosed and how you can get access to this information. Please review it carefully.

If you have any questions about this Notice please contact our Privacy Contact Person.

This Notice of Privacy Practice describes how we may use and disclose your protected health information to carry out treatment, payment or health care operations and for other purposes that are permitted or required by law. It also describes your rights to access and control your protected health information. “Protected health information” is information about you, including demographic information, which may identify you and that relates to your past, present or future physical or mental health or condition and related heath care services.

We are required to abide by the terms of this Notice of Privacy Practices. We may change the terms of our notice, at any time. The new notice will be effective for all protected health information that we maintain at that time. Upon your request, we will provide you with any revised Notice of Privacy Practices by call the office and requesting that a revised copy be sent to you in the mail.

 **1.0 Uses and Disclosures of Protected Health Information**

 **1.1 Uses and Disclosures of Protected Health Information Based Upon Your Written Consent**

Your protected health information may be used and disclosed by TTPM for the purpose of providing health care services to you. Your protected health information may also be used and disclosed to pay your health care bills and to support the operation of TTPM.

The following are examples of the types of uses and disclosures of your protected health information that TTPM is permitted to make once you have signed our consent form. These examples are not meant to be exhaustive, but to describe the types of uses and disclosures that may be made by our office once you have provided consent.

 _Treatment:_ We will use and disclose your protected health information to provide, coordinate, or manage your health care and any related services. This includes the coordination or management of your health care with a third party that has already obtained your permission to have access to your protected health information. We will also disclose protected health information to other physicians who may be treating you when we have the necessary permission from you to disclose your protected health information. We may release medical information about you to a friend or family that is involved in your medical care. _Payment:_ Your protected health information will be used, as needed, to obtain payment for your health care services. This may included certain activities that your health insurance plan may undertake before it approves or pays for the health care services we performed. Such as; making a determination of eligibility or coverage of insurance benefits, reviewing services provided to you for medical necessity, and undertaking utilization review activities. We may also release medical information to someone who helps pay for your care. _Healthcare Operations:_ We may use or disclose, as needed, your protected health information in order to support the business activities of TTPM. These activities include, but are not limited to, quality assessment activities, employee review activities, employee training and conducting or arranging for other business activities. 

We will share your protected health information with third party “business associates” that perform various activities. Whenever an arrangement between our office and a business associate involves the use or disclosure of your protected health information, we will have a written contract that contains terms that will protect your privacy of your protected health information.

 **1.2 Uses and Disclosures of Protected Health Information Based upon Your Written Authorization**

Other uses and disclosure of your protected health information will be made only with your written authorization, unless otherwise permitted or required by law as described below. You may revoke this authorization, at any time, in writing, except to the extent that TTPM has taken an action in reliance on the use or disclosure indicated in the authorization.

 **1.3 Other Permitted and Required Uses and Disclosures That May Be Made Without Your Consent, Authorization or Opportunity to Object**

 _Communication Barriers:_ We may use and disclose your protected health information if TTPM attempts to obtain consent from you but is unable to do so due to substantial communication barriers and if TTPM determines, using professional judgment, that you intend to consent to use of disclosure under the circumstances. 

**1.4 We may use or disclose your protected health information in the following situations without consent or authorization. These situations include:**

 _Required by Law:_ We may use or disclose your protected health information to the extent that the law requires the use or disclosure. The use or disclosure will be made in compliance with the law and will be limited to the relevant requirements of the law. You will be notified, as required by law, of any such uses or disclosers. _Public Health:_ We may disclose your protected health information for public heath activities and purposes to a public health authority that is permitted by law to collect or receive the information. The disclosure will be made for the purpose of controlling disease, injury or disability. We may also disclose your protected health information, if directed by the public health authority, to a foreign government agency that is collaborating with the public health authority. _Communicable Diseases:_ We may disclose you protected health information, if authorized by law, to a person who may have been exposed to a communicable disease or may otherwise be at risk of contracting the disease or condition. _Health Oversight:_ We may disclose protected health information to a health oversight agency for activities authorized by law, such as audits, investigations, and inspections. Oversight agencies seeking this information include government agencies that oversee the health care system, government benefit programs, other government regulatory programs and civil rights laws. _Abuse and Neglect:_ We may disclose your protected health information to a public health authority that is authorized by law to receive reports of child abuse or neglect. In addition, we may disclose your protected health information if we believe that you have been a victim of abuse, neglect or domestic violence to the government entity or agency authorized to receive such information. In this case, the disclosure will be made consistent with the requirements of applicable federal and state laws. _Food and Drug Administration:_ We may disclose your protected health information to a person or company required by the Food and Drug Administration to report adverse events, products defects or problems, biologic product deviations, track products; to enable product recalls; to make repairs or replacements, or to conduct post marketing surveillance, as required.

_Legal Proceedings:_ We may disclose protected health information in the course of any judicial or administrative proceeding, in response to an order of a court or administrative tribunal (to the extent such disclosure is expressly authorized), in certain conditions in response to a subpoena, discovery request or other lawful process.  
Law Enforcement: We may also disclose protected health information, so long as applicable legal requirements are met, for law enforcement purposes. These law enforcement purposes include (1) legal processes and otherwise required by law, (2) limited information requests for identification and location purposes, (3) pertaining to victims of a crime, (4) suspicion that death occurred as a result of criminal conduct, (5) in the event that a crime occurs on the premises of the practices, and (6) medical emergency (not on the Practice’s premises) and it is likely that a crime has occurred. _Coroners, Funeral Directors, and Organ Donation:_ We may disclose protected health information to a coroner or medical examiner for identification purposes, determining cause of death or for the coroner or medical examiner to perform other duties authorized by law. We may also disclose protected health information to a funeral director, as authorized by law, in order to permit the funeral director to carry out their duties. We may disclose such information in reasonable anticipation of death. Protected health information may be used and disclosed for cadaver organ, eye or tissue donation purposes. _Criminal Activity:_ Consistent with applicable federal and state laws, we may disclose your protected health information, if we believe that the use of disclosure is necessary to prevent or lessen a serious and imminent threat to the health or safety of a person of the public. We may also disclose protected health information if it is necessary for law enforcement authorities to identify or apprehend an individual. _Military Activity and National Security:_ When appropriate conditions apply, we may use or disclose your protected health information of individuals who are Armed Forces personnel (1) for activities deemed necessary by appropriate military command authorities; (2) for the purpose of a determination by the Department of Veterans Affairs of your eligibility for benefits, or (3) to foreign military authority if you are a member of that foreign military services. We may also disclose your protected health information to authorized federal officials for conducting national security and intelligence activities, including for the provision of protective services to the President or others legally authorized. _Workers’ Compensation:_ Your protected health information may be disclosed by us a s authorized to comply with workers’ compensation laws and other similar legally-established programs. _Inmates:_ We may use or disclose your protected health information if you are an inmate of a correctional facility and your physician created or received your protected health information in the course of providing care to you.

 **2.0 Your Rights**

Following is a statement of your rights with respect to your protected health information and a brief description of how you may exercise these rights.

 **2.1 You have the right to inspect and copy your protected health information.**

This means you may inspect and obtain a copy of protected health information about you that is contained in a designated record set for as long as we maintain the protected health information. A “designated record set” contains medical and billing records and any other records that the practice uses for making decisions about you.

Under federal law, however, you may not inspect or copy the following records; psychotherapy notes; information compiled in reasonable anticipation of, or use in, a civil, criminal, or administrative action or proceeding, and protected health information that is subject to law that prohibits access to protected health information. Depending on the circumstances, a decision to deny access may be reviewable. In some circumstances, a decision to deny access may be reviewable. In some circumstances, you may have a right to have this decision reviewed. Please contact our Privacy Contact if you have questions about access to your medical record.

 **2.2 You have the right to request a restriction of your protected health information.**

This means you may ask us not to us or disclose any part of your protected health information for the purposes of treatment, payment or healthcare operations. You may also request that any part of your protected health information not be disclosed to family members or friends who may be involved in your care or for notification purposes as described in this Notice of Privacy Practices. Your request must state the specific restriction requested and to whom you want the restriction to apply.

TTPM is not required to agree to a restriction that you may request. If TTPM believes it is in your best interest to permit use and disclosure of your protected health information, your protected health information will not be restricted. If TTPM does agree to the requested restriction, we may not use or disclose your protected health information in violation of that restriction unless it is needed to provide emergency treatment. You may request a restriction in writing to our Privacy Contact.

 **2.3 You have the right to request to receive confidential communications from us by alternative means or at an alternative location.**

We will accommodate reasonable requests. We may also condition this accommodation by asking you for information as to how payment will be handled or specification of an alternative address or other method of contact. We will not request an explanation from you as to the basis for the request. Please make this request in writing to our Privacy Contact.

 **2.4 You may have the right to have TTPM amend your protected health information.**

This means you may request an amendment of protected health information about you in a designated record set for as long as we maintain this information. In certain cases, we may deny your request for an amendment. If we deny your request for amendment, you have the right to file a statement of disagreement with us and we may prepare a rebuttal. Please contact or Privacy Contact to determine if you have questions about amending your medical record.

 **2.5 You have the right to receive an accounting of certain disclosures we have made, if any, of your protected health information.**

This right applies to disclosures for purposes other than treatment, payment or healthcare operations as described in this Notice of Privacy Practices. It excludes disclosures we may have made to you, to family members or fiends involved in your care, or for notification purposes. You have the right to receive specific information regarding these disclosures that occurred after April 14, 2003. You may request a shorter timeframe. The right to receive this information is subject to certain exceptions, restrictions and limitations.

You have the right to receive a paper copy of this notice from us, upon request.

 **3.0 Complaints**

You may complain to the Secretary of Health and Human Services or us if you believe your privacy rights have been violated by us. You may file a complaint with us by notifying our privacy contact of your complaint. We will not retaliate against you for filing a complaint.

 **4.0 Changes to this Notice**

We reserve the right to change this notice. We reserve the right to make the revised or changed notice effective for medical information we already have about you as well as any information we receive about you in the future. We will post a copy of the current notice in our lobby and on our website.

You may contact our Privacy Contact Person, at 607-733-6094, for further information about the complaint process.

This notice becomes effective on April 14, 2003.

This notice was amended on May 13, 2003.
